Register of the Bruce Walker papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Bruce Walker papers
1958-2011
2006C8
Hoover Institution Archives
6 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 oversize folder, 1 painting (3.2 linear feet)
Writings, instructional and propaganda material, printed matter, photographs, video tapes, and memorabilia, relating to Central Intelligence Agency programs to train Tibetan guerrillas.
Walker, Bruce, 1932-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees Records, Hoover Institution Archives
S. Fawl typescript, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1932 August 29 Born, Bronxville, New York
1953 Graduated from DePauw University in Greencastle, Indiana, with a major in economics and minor in Spanish Second lieutenant, United States Marines
1954-1955 Stationed in Korea with the First Marine Air Wing. Promoted to first lieutenant
1955 Honorably discharged at Treasure Island
1956-1973 Case officer, Central Intelligence Agency (CIA)
1957-1959 Assigned to U.S. Consulate in Guayaquil, Ecuador
1960 Transferred to Near East Division and started work on STCIRCUS Enrolled in Tibetan studies courses at the University of Washington, Seattle
1962 Student, Namgyal Institute of Tibetology in Gangtok, Sikkim, India Private audience with the Dalai Lama
1962-1964 Trained Tibetans at Camp Hale, Colorado, as part of STCIRCUS project
1965-1966 Worked at Tibetan project desk, where one of his duties was to oversee the Cornell University program for Tibetans under the STCIRCUS project
1966 Assigned to U.S. Embassy in New Delhi, India, using State Department cover, as the replacement STCIRCUS representative at the Joint Operations Center
1968 Six month leave of absence from CIA
1969 Transferred to Hong Kong desk in China Operations
1971 Assigned to U.S. Consulate-General in Hong Kong as a case officer under State Department cover
1973 Resigned from CIA Married Mary Frances Doyle
1974 Moved to San Francisco
1974-1988 Worked in several business development departments of Bechtel Corporation
1980-1988 Member, Board of Directors, Merola Opera Program of the San Francisco Opera
1985 Established a Merola scholarship endowment fund
1994 Became a volunteer at the San Francisco Performing Arts Library & Museum
2004 Elected president of the board of the San Francisco Performing Arts Library & Museum
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers document Bruce Walker's role in STCIRCUS, a Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) project to give support to the Tibetan resistance by training Tibetan guerrillas, providing arms to the Chushi Gangdruk fighters, and using radio teams to communicate information to the CIA. Bruce Walker's initial assignment for the project was to transfer Tibetans to Camp Hale, Colorado, for training in "high-speed radio operations, clandestine communications, small arms, map reading, tradecraft," and other skills, including parachuting (curriculum vitae, box 1, folder 1). In 1962, Walker became part of the training staff at Camp Hale.
The arrangement of the STCIRCUS file is based on the order of materials found in a partial inventory of the collection created by Bruce Walker, although the arrangement does not exactly match this list. The file includes photographs at Camp Hale and of Chushi Gangdruk fighters, clippings, a report by Sam Curry, and propaganda booklets. Detailed descriptions of materials in the collection can be found in Walker's inventory (box 1, folder 2).
Items not listed in Walker's inventory of September 2005 can be found in the Incremental material. Several folders include detailed container lists. The Oversize material contains cloth flags with the logo of the Chushi Gangdruk and the painting "The Secret PLA Pouch Heads for CIA's K Building, West Tibet" by Keith Woodcock.
United States. Central Intelligence Agency.; Guerrillas--China--Tibet--Autonomous Region.; Secret service--United States.; Tibet (China)--History--1951-
- STCIRCUS file, 1958-2005 (Box 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes partial inventory by Bruce Walker, photographs, clippings, English-Tibetan dictionary, reports, transcripts, and audiovisual material related to a CIA project to train Tibetan guerrilla fighters.
  - Curriculum vitae of Bruce Walker, 2005 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Partial inventory, compiled by Bruce Walker, 2005 (Folder 1: 2)
  - STCIRCUS bibliography, 2005 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Articles (Box 1)
    - John Kenneth Knaus, "Official Policies and Covert Programs,", 2003 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1961-1988 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1991-1997 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1998-1999 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 2000-2004 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Video recording. The Shadow Circus: The CIA in Tibet, undated (Folder 1: 9)
    VHS tape
  - Reunion of STCIRCUS personnel in Las Vegas, 2004 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Photographs (Box 1-2)
    - Camp Hale, Colorado (Box 1-2)
      - General, 1961-1964 (Folder 1: 11)
      - Slides by Bruce Walker, 1961-1964 (Folder 1: 12)
      - Black and white prints by Bruce Walker, 1961-1964 (Folder 2: 1)
      - Black and white prints, miscellaneous, 1961-1964 (Folder 2: 2)
      - Reproductions by Bruce Walker, 1961-1964 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Cornell University: Tibetan trainees, 1964-1966 (Folder 2: 4)
      By Bruce Walker
    - Chushi Gangdruk fighters, 1958 (Folder 2: 5)
      Photocopies of photographs
    - Chushi Gangdruk general meeting, New Delhi, 1997 (Folder 2: 6)
      Photocopy of photograph
  - Dhokham Chushi Gangdruk (New York): pamphlets and cover letter from Kalsang Gyatotsang, 2004 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Propaganda booklets and brochures (Box 2)
    - Booklets in Tibetan language, 1963 (Folder 2: 8)
      Five brochures by Ken Knaus and STRANCH trainees
    - Brochures in Tibetan language, undated (Folder 2: 9)
    - Brochure, circa 1963 (Folder 2: 10)
  - First-aid brochure in Tibetan language, undated (Folder 2: 11)
  - Maps of Tibet region, undated (Folder 2: 12)
  - English-Tibetan dictionary (Box 2)
    Prepared by Bruce Walker and Tibetan interpreters and trainees at Camp Hale, Colorado
    - Drafts, 1964 (Folder 2: 13)
    - Printed version, 1964 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Drawings and text by Tibetan trainees, Stranch, Nepal, undated (Folder 2: 15)
  - Transcript, "The Science of Spying," NBL-TV, 1965 May 4 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Anthony Poshepny (also known as Tony Poe) file (Box 2)
    - News articles, 1972-2000 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Death and funeral, 2003 (Folder 2: 18)
      Includes photographs
  - Report by Sam Curry, undated (Folder 2: 19)
  - Typescript, "Tears of the Lotus: The Savaging of Tibet" by Roger E. McCarthy, 1994 (Folder 3: 1-2)
    Two copies. Includes correspondence
  - Sound recording. Interview of Alan Farley by Ken Knaus. "Orphans of the Cold War,", 1999 (Folder 3: 3)
    Compact sound cassette
- Incremental material, 1967-2011 (Box 3-4)
  Includes materials not listed in Walker's partial inventory of September 2005, such as clippings, video tapes, and correspondence.
  - Articles, 2008-2009 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Booklet on Archangel aircraft, 2007 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Correspondence and articles, 1994-2006, undated (Folder 4: 1)
    Includes correspondence about "Tears of the Lotus" manuscript
  - Materials received in 2008, 1998-2008, undated (Folder 4: 2)
  - Materials received in 2011, 1967-2011 (Folder 4: 3)
    Includes articles, maps, and STCIRCUS bibliography
  - Video recording. "Meeting with the Dalai Lama," with Roger E. McCarthy and Mikel Dunham, 1999 March 23 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Video recording. Talk by Roger E. McCarthy at the University of Toronto, 1998 October 1 (Folder 4: 5)
- Oversize material, 1961, undated (Box 5)
  - Cloth flags, undated (Box 5)
    Two cotton flags containing the Chushi Gangdruk logo of crossed swords in black on a solid orange background. One flag contains a motto
  - Painting. "The Secret PLA Pouch Heads for CIA's K Building, West Tibet," by Keith Woodcock, 1961 October 25
    Located on wall in Tower 16
  - Operational maps of Tibet printed on silk, undated
- Additional incremental material (Box 6-7)
  Material not yet described.